压制：Ξ血龍吟д  字幕：天羽
本人董建华，谨此宣誓
I, Tung Chee Wah, do solemnly swearto serve as the
本人就任中华人民共和国香港特别 行政区行政长官
Chief Executive of the Hong Kong Special Administration Region (HKSAR) of the People's Republic of China,
并当拥护中华人民共和国香港特别 行政区基本法
and to support the Basic Law of the HKSAR of the People's Republic of China,
效忠中华人民共和国香港特别行政区
and swear allegiance to the HKSAR of the People's Republic of China,
尽忠职守、遵守法律
to perform my duty to the best of my ability and obey the law,
廉洁奉公为香港特别行政区服务
to honestly serve the HKSAR,
中华人民共和国、中央人民政府
responsible to the Central People's Government,
和香港特别行政区负责
the People's Republic of China and the HKSAR
董先生（香港特别行政区首长）
Mr Tung (Chief Executive of the HKSAR),
那些少年犯犯案时还很年轻， 心智未成熟
these juvenile offenders were very young when they committed their crimes
但是他们的刑期却比成年犯还要长
Yet theirterms were more severe than those for adult criminals
是吗？粱议员，怎么你不早来找我？
Really, Councillor? Why didn't you let me know earlier?
其实他们每个人都写过信给你
In fact each of them wrote to you
不过可能你太忙，没时间处理
You were probably too busy to deal with it
我自己也写过三封信给你
I wrote you three times too
他们从没有放弃过自己， 而且每个人都很有上进心
They've never given up on themselves. They are all very industrious
你帮帮他们减刑，给他们一个机会 重新做人吧
Help them to remit their sentences; give them a chance at a new life
我有权减刑的吗？
Do I have the right to remit sentences?
基本法第四十八条，写明我们的 特首是有权的
Article 48 of the Basic Law states that our Chief Executive has the right
李国能（香港终审庭首席大法官） 是个好法官
Andrew Li (Chief Justice of the Court of Final Appeal) is a good judge,
在法律界有很高声望
and has a high reputation in the realm of Law
市民也很满意他当香港终审庭 的首席法官
People are delighted he is the Chief Justice in the Court of Final Appeal
他所建议的刑期，我可以改吗？
Can I change the sentences he handed down?
他们有没有宗教信仰？
Are they religious?
有宗教信仰还好一点
It would be betterforthem if they are
最少精神有寄托
That they at least have some mental support to cling to
1985年
Year of 1985
机灵点好不好？说好去偷铜嘛！
Be smart, won't you? We're supposed to be stealing copper!
绳子也不带一条，你怎么做事的？
You didn't even bring a rope; what's the matter with you?
你这个老大怎么带小弟的？！真没用！
How did you become the chief, huh? Useless!
老大！
Chief!
什么事？
What?
你看！
Look!
老大，铜这么重！
Copper's so heavy,
不如去抢劫！
why don't we just go and rob them?
好呀！老大
Yeah! Chief!
有意思！
Why not?
搞定了那妞！
We fixed that chick!
快跑！跑呀…
Let's go! Run...
妈妈，我约了同学去看电影， 我现在出去了
Mom, I'm going to a movie with my classmate, I'm going now
你早点回来呀！
Be home early!
是！
OK!
誉玲，你干什么？鬼鬼祟祟的
What are you doing, Yue-ling? So sneaky!
藏著些什么？
What are you hiding?
这是你的？！
Is this yours?
我不能穿校服去的
I can't go in my uniform
我穿校服去看电影，同学会笑我的
They'll laugh at me forthat
你怕被同学笑你？
Is that what you're worried about?
好好的校服你不穿，你穿这个， 干嘛妖里妖气的
You don't want your uniform; all you fancy are cheap dresses like this!
就像个飞女一样！
And you make yourself look like a street kid
你不怕被人强奸吗？
Aren't you worried about getting raped?
我怎么会给你穿？！
I can't let you wear it!
我剪烂它！
I must cut it up!
放手…放手
Let go! Let go!
你这个死丫头，我这么辛苦把 你带来香港
Damn you! I spent so much effort bringing you to Hong Kong
我日日夜夜干活
I work like a dog
你居然不给我好好的读书
Yet you don't like school
你这死丫头，你要把我气死了
You damned girl, you really drive me nuts
将来还有什么希望
宝马山今晨发现双尸命案
Two bodies were found this morning in Braemar Hill
一对外籍男女被发现倒毙在草丛中
Aforeign couple was found dead in the bushes.
是你要带我来香港的
It was you who brought me to Hong Kong
还说这里是天堂
You said this was paradise
我每天上课，都被人家在叫我“灿妹”
People call me country girl in school
这里没有一个是好人
People here are bad,
连你也是一样！
including you!
出去买酱油都让我穿校服
I even have to wear my uniform to go to the corner store
谁呀？
Who is it?
阿琼，是我呀！
It's me, King!
跟你在同一生产线工作的那个呀
We worked on the same assembly line
什么事？
What do you want?
阿琼，他是粱先生，她是张小姐
This is Mr Leung, King! This is Miss Cheung!
他们正在帮助我们的
He's helping us
粱先生，厂方很刻薄我们
The factory is very mean to us
你明天跟我们一起罢工吧
Why don't you go on strike with us tomorrow?
我现在没有上班，已经是罢工了
I have stopped work, this is a strike
工人的权益应该靠工人自己去争取
Workers should fight forthemselves
呆在家里不上班
The factory and society won't understand exactly what you need...
厂方跟社会根本不会明白 你们究竟需要些什么
when you just stop going to work
如果钟表厂所有的工人 都出来静坐抗议
The factory wouldn't dare to exploit your rights...
厂方就不敢胡乱的剥削 你们应有的权益
if all watch workers made a sit-in protest
拿开它…我怕呀！
Take it away! I'm scared!
别怕！
Don't worry!
捉紧袋口就行了
Just hold the bag tight
待会带你出去玩好吗？
Do you want me to take you out to play?
好呀！我要去海洋公园、去看电影、 去滑冰
Yeah! I want to go to Ocean Park, to a movie and skating
行…行！去哪儿玩都行
Fine... fine! Whereveryou want...
只要你乖乖的听话就行了
as long as you're good
表姨父，我觉得全香港只有 你一个人对我好
You're the only person in Hong Kong who's nice to me, uncle!
如果你听话，我对你会更好
If you behave, I'll treat you even better
怎么你的内裤这么大的？！
Why are your panties so big?
我哪有自己的内裤啊
I don't have my own underwear
我是穿别人的
They are somebody else's
如果你乖的话，我改天买些新的给你
I'll buy you some if you behave
午间新闻：较早前在宝马山发现的 双尸案死者
Good afternoon, police confirm that the couple found dead in Braemar Hill...
警方已经证实为英童学校的预科生
were Form 6 students at an English Foundation School
父母是在香港工作的英国人
Their parents are British, working in Hong Kong
当他们知悉儿女遇害的消息
After learning the news,
女死者的母亲当场晕倒
the dead girl's motherfainted,
男死者的父亲情绪激动
and the dead boy's father was very angry
杀害我儿子和他的女朋友的人 应该被判死刑
Whoever did this to my son and his girlfriend deserve a death penalty
他们的行为连禽兽也不如
They'd be put to death, they're animals, they shouldn't be walking around!
香港到处都是坏人
Villains are everywhere in Hong Kong,
我们这些成年人也经常受人欺骗
even adults are always getting taken
你乖的话我会很疼你的
I'll treat you very nicely if you're a good girl
我们的事你千万不要告诉金姨
Don't tell Aunt Kim about us
如果金姨死了， 你会不会对我好一点？
Will you treat me better if Aunt Kim dies?
从来没有欢呼声加冕 勤劳未可得到幸福
There have never been cheers of support, Hard work has not brought happiness
浮沉在社会底处 历尽了压迫心不死
Floating at the bottom of society, the heart didn't die of countless woes
埋藏在我心中的激愤 犹如睡醒的母狮
The anger in me... is like a lioness woken from sleep
同行在抗争的火线 命运已紧紧结连
Walking the picket line together, ourfates are tied
作战同往这一刻 青山、海、与天
The moment we're fighting the battle together, the green mountain, the sea, and the sky
在世界画上这一笔 欢呼响震天
This is the mark we leave in the world. The cheers shake the sky
我的膀胱有病嘛
My bladder has problems
那个该死的组长一天只许我上两次厕所
That goddamned group leader only lets me go to the washroom twice a day
其实这次的罢工
In fact this strike
在近几年香港的工人运动来说， 是一次突破来
is a breakthrough forthe workers' movement
我们在很短的时间内 已经召集了很多工友
We recruited many workers forthe sit-in protest
在工厂门口静坐抗议
in a very short time
反对厂方各种不合理的待遇
We object to the very unjust rules in the factory
埋藏在我心中的激愤 犹如睡醒的母狮
The anger in me... is like a lioness woken from sleep
同行在抗争的火线 命运已紧紧结连
Walking the picket line together, ourfates are tied
作战同往这一刻 青山、海、与天
The moment we're fighting the battle together, the green mountain, the sea, and the sky
在世界画上这一笔 欢呼响震天
This is the mark we leave in the world. The cheers shake the sky
粱先生，没有提及我们的新闻啊
Our protest is not mentioned,
全都是宝马山的双尸案
Mr. Leung, only the Braemar Hill couple
都刊登在主页头条呢！
All the front-page headlines are taken
真的没有我们的新闻呀？
There is really nothing about us
你找清楚了没有？
Have you read them thoroughly?
真的看清楚了，你看！
Yes, I did!
张有铭，十六岁
Cheung Yau-ming, aged 16,
被控于一九八五年四月十七日
was charged with killing the British couple, John McBrady and Helen Hayes...
在宝马山杀害英籍男子约翰麦伯迪
in Braemar Hill on April 17, 1985. The accused is guilty of murder...
及英籍女子海伦希斯
in Braemar Hill on April 17th 1985.
谋杀罪名成立
The accused is guilty of murder.
由于你还未成年，本席判你
Since you're not an adult,
“等候英女皇发落”
you are to be detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
1997年——回归前6个月
Year of 1997, 6 months before Handover
别哭！
Don't cry!
再哭就喂你吃屎
I'll feed you shit if you do!
别再哭！再哭我真的会给你吃屎
Stop crying! I'm really gonna feed you shit if you don't!
再哭？就打死你
I'll kill you if you don't stop!
张有铭，我是你在公开大学的同学 张誉玲
Cheung Yau-ming, I'm Yue-ling, your classmate at the Open University
在学生报读到你的文章
Having read your article in the student press,
我觉得你的文字很生动
I find your language very lively
不知何故，我幻想你是 一个弹钢琴的人
I don't know why I imagined you were a piano player...
我很想写封信给你
and wanted to write you a letter
但是当我查到你地址的时候
When I found out your address
我才知道你原来是一个囚犯
I realised you were a prisoner
当我参加散文比赛输给你的时候
When I lost to you in the prose competition,
我又再次拿你的文章来看
I read your article again
忽然间，我很想更了解你
Suddenly, I wanted to know more about you
我很冒昧的写了一封信给你
I only sent you an unsolicited letter
想不到，你很爽快的给 我一个见面的机会
I didn't expect you'd be willing to meet me so quickly
探监吗？那边去！
Jail visit? That way!
请出示身分证
Your identification card, please!
你来看谁的？
Who are you visiting?
张有铭
Cheung Yau-ming
你知不知他的编号？
Do you know his number?
我有一些书是给他的
I brought him some books
这本硬皮书不能带进去
Hard-cover books are not allowed
好的
OK!
领回你的身分证
Here's your identification card!
谢谢！
Thank you!
这些东西都不能拿进去， 你放进十三号储物柜里
None of these are allowed. Put them in locker no. 13
谢谢！
Thank you!
把身上的金属物品放下
Leave all metal stuff here
举起双手，高一点…
Raise your hands. Higher!
行了
OK!
拿回钥匙吧！
Take your keys back!
我是张誉玲呀！
I'm Cheung Yue-ling!
我是张誉玲
谢谢你来看我
Thanks for coming to see me!
其实我早就想来
I wanted to come long ago
不过早阵子很忙
But I was very busy
你不是香港人？
You are not a local?
我十多岁的时候跟我妈妈 从大陆来了香港
I came from the Mainland in my teens, with my Mom
我曾经很努力的学习广东话
I once tried very hard to learn Cantonese
我想像一个香港人嘛！
Because I wanted to be like a local!
但是现在我觉得不用了
But now I find there's no need
我只想像我自己就行了
ljust want to be myself
大家都是中国人罢了！
We are Chinese, after all!
那你会听普通话嘛？
So do you speak Potunghua?
你翻译的题目选什么？
What topic did you choose fortranslation?
法律
Law
法律？！
Law?
我听到法律就害怕了
I feel a chill in my bones whenever I hearthe word
没办法了，我们在这里每天 都会接触到法律
I can't help it! We come across it here every day
难怪很多监友都说
No wonder a lot of my friends here say...
他们两母子每次见面都像 拍悲情电影一样
that every mother-and-son meeting is like a tragic movie
你呢？你跟你家人见面的时 是演“喜剧”的吗？
What about you? Is it a comedy when you and yourfamily meet?
我在这儿已经十二年了
I've been here for 12 years
我的家人从来没有来过看我
My family never came to visit me
我想，他们
I think, they...
已经忘了我
already forgot about me
你什么时候出狱呀？
When will you finish serving yourterm?
对不起！誉玲
Sorry, Yue-ling!
我不太会说话
I'm not very talkative
你对著我那半个小时，是不是很闷呀？
Was it boring to spend 30 minutes with me?
其实在你来之前的几天
In fact, I started practising talking to myself...
我就开始跟自己练习说话
a few days before you came
自从十六岁我进来以后
Ever since I came here at 16,
就一直没机会跟女性说话
I have never had a chance to talk to women
是我觉得这不是最重要的
But I don't think this is the most important thing
因为我心里只是惦念著我的家人
Because I often miss my family very much
在见到你以后，我忽然间想起 一件事情
After meeting you, I suddenly think that...
我的家人可能已经忘了我了
my family might have forgotten about me
但是，我现在还是很记得 我亲生妈妈是什么模样的
But I still remember what my natural mother looked like
誉玲，我不是你幻想中那个会 弹钢琴的人
Yue-ling, I'm not the piano player of your imagination
但是我懂得把你的样子记下来
But I know how to make a drawing to rememberyourface
那天你问我什么时候可以出狱
That day you asked me when I would finish serving my term
一时之间我真是不能回答你
Out of the blue, I really couldn't answer
因为我是被判等英女皇发落的
Because I am detained at Her Majesty's pleasure,
但是到现在，我还没有刑期
I haven't been sentenced
发仔…发仔
Fatt... Fatt
什么？
What?
你的英文好，不如你写信给英女皇吧？
Your English is good, why don't you send the Queen a letter?
你以为“等候英女皇发落”
You think detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
就是真的要英女皇来判案吗？
really refers to the Queen?
我们要囚禁多久
The length of our jail terms depends on
是由彭定康（香港总督）决定的
Chris Patten (Governor of HK)
铭仔，牙膏还给你！
Yourtoothpaste, Ming!
在石壁监狱里
In Shek Pik Prison,
还有几个像我一样
there are several others detained at
被判“等候英女皇发落”的犯人
Her Majesty's pleasure
最近我们这帮等候发落的犯人
Recently, prisoners like us, detained at Her Majesty's pleasure,
给殖民政府几个部门踢来踢去
are being bounced between departments of the colonial government
我们很担心，英国人离开香港以后
Afterthe British leave Hong Kong, we are very worried about...
将来的特区政府会怎样处置我们…
what the SAR government will do with us
所以我们很希望政府在回归前
So we really hope our sentences
可以给我们一个确定的刑期
will be set before the Handover
不要让我们无了期地等下去
And we'll not be kept waiting for ever
要不然，我们的命运真的不知会怎么样
Otherwise we really don't know what ourfate will be
还记得寄了几封信吗？
Do you remember how many letters you sent?
寄了一百多封，政府拿我们当皮球踢！
A hundred-odd letters, the government kicks us around like footballs!
寄了有什么用？！一点作用都没有
What's the point? It's no use at all!
外面正在搞回归（英国人把香港 主权交还中国）
The Handover (HK returns to China) is approaching
谁会管我们！
Who'll care for us?
67544，有人来看你
67544, someone is paying you a visit
有什么可以帮忙的？
May I help you?
你好！我找粱忠勤议员
Hi! I would like to speak to the Councillor, Leung Chung-ken
粱先生在开会，请等一下
He's at a meeting, please wait for a while
粱先生！
Mr. Leung!
粱先生，有人找你
Mr. Leung, someone is here foryou
知道了，谢谢！
OK, thanks!
粱先生，十楼太低了
The 10th floor is too low, Mr. Leung
替我想一想办法再高几层
Can you help me to get several stories higher?
陈先生，粱议员当时帮你搬 上楼已经不容易的了
Getting you moved in was already difficult, Mr. Chan!
现在上了楼，你又嫌太低
Now that you have, and you find the level too low
你自己到房委会重新申请吧！
Go apply again to the Housing Authority yourself!
粱先生，你的职员怎么这样子？ 我可投了你一票的
How can your member of staff say that, Mr. Leung? I voted foryou
陈先生晚上要上班，白天想安静的睡觉
Mr. Chan works at night and wants some quiet sleep in the daytime
我们该体谅他的
We should understand that
这么说就对了，我没白投你的票
That's the point! My vote is worth it!
粱议员，B座粪渠堵了很久了
Councillor, Block B's pipes are still blocked,
何时帮我们修？
when will you help us?
我会叫房屋署跟进的了，放心吧！
I will ask the Housing Department to follow up. Don't worry!
好的，谢谢你！
OK! Thank you!
好了，时间差不多了
OK, time is running out
粱议员还要开会，你们回去等消息吧
The Councillor has a meeting to attend, we'll get back to you
我们会跟进的，放心吧！
We'll follow up, not to worry!
谢谢你们！
Thank you!
粱先生，全靠你了
Mr. Leung, I depend on you
放心吧！
Don't worry!
谢谢！
Thank you!
你好！你是不是粱先生？
Hi! Are you Mr. Leung?
是的！什么事？
Yes! How can I help you?
这封信是我朋友托我交给你的
My friend wants me to give you this letter
好！
Fine!
我好像也收过一封
I seem to have received a copy too
这些人现在很害怕九七年 后的法律衔接问题
These people are worried about legal problems after 1997
政府到现在都没给他们确定的刑期
And the government hasn't yet given them determinate sentences
这封信我看过的
I read it
写来写去都是什么不人道、 不公平或不合理等等
It's all about inhumanity, injustice, intolerance, all that jazz
可是他们都是杀人犯呀！
But they are all murderers, after all!
他们也知道自己该受惩罚
They should have known they would be punished
但是犯人也是人嘛！
But prisoners are humans too!
如果把他们无限期地关押下去
It's inhumane...
这也是不人道的！
if they are detained indefinitely
而且国际人权法庭也裁定
And the International Court of Human Rights also ruled that...
无限期押后判刑是违反人权法的
indefinite detention violates the law of human rights
他们没有刑期的吗？
Don't they have a term?
“他们被判的是““等候英女皇发落“““
They are detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
“本来““等候英女皇发落“““
Detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
是给那些心智不成熟的青少年犯 有改过自新的机会
primarily gives mentally immature youngoffenders a chance to correct themselves
但是政府到现在还没有 给他们确定刑期
Since the government still hasn't defined theirterm,
那么等候英女皇发落就 变成了无限期坐牢
detained at Her Majesty's pleasure has turned into indefinite imprisonment
有的人已经关押了二十年， 还不知道自己的刑期
Some have been detained for 20 years and yet still don't know theirterms
全香港有多少个这种犯人？
How many prisoners of this kind are there in Hong Kong?
二十三个！
23!
粱先生，青衣（香港社区之一） 有二十三万人
Tsing Yi (a Hong Kong community) has a population of 230,000, Mr. Leung
粱先生，我这里有一份资料，你看看
Take a look at the information I've got here, Mr. Leung!
这些都是香港重犯的记录
All these are records of serious criminals in Hong Kong
这些抢劫银行，杀了警察的成年重犯
These adult criminals robbed a bank, and killed a cop
最长判了四十六年
The longest they got was 46 years
扣了假期、假释等等
After deductions of holidays and parole,
他们实际上只须服刑二十三年
actually they only need to suffer punishment for 23 years
但是那些心智不成熟的青少年犯 却无限期给关押著
But those young offenders are detained indefinitely
还有，粱先生，你看这案子！
Also, look at this case, Mr. Leung!
八七年元朗的一宗械斗案， 法庭判了谋杀罪
The court judged an armed fight in Yuen Long in 1987 to be a murder case
第一被告给判了死刑
The first accused was sentenced to death
他是成年犯，其他三个少年犯…
But he was an adult offender; the other 3 young offenders...
给判的是“等候英女皇发落”
were detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
到了九零年，同案的成年犯 获得港督特赦
In 1990, the adult offender in that case received the Governor's amnesty...
改判二十五年
and was sentenced to 25 years
扣掉三分之一假期
After deducting 1/3 of it for holidays,
这个成年犯的实际刑期只有十八年
This adult offender's actual term was 18 years
他已经快出狱了
He will soon be released
但是当年被他操纵的孩子已关押了十年
But the kids under his control have been detained for 10 years
到现在还不知道自己的刑期
and yet still don't know about theirterms
小铭，你快去叫所有等候发落的犯人
Ming, call all the detainees as soon as possible,
让他们通知自己的家人
notify theirfamilies...
在星期日到粱忠勤的办公室开会
to meet in Leung Chung-ken's office on Sunday
没想到你会帮我
I didn't expect you to help
其实我只是一个犯人
I'm just a prisoner
没坐牢以前只是一个小混混
I was just a street kid before coming here
你别这么说自己嘛
Don't say that
我在孤儿院长大的
I grew up in an orphanage
九岁那年，爸爸和后妈把我接回家
At nine, Dad and my stepmothertook me home...
原来是为了申请大一点的廉租屋
just so they could apply for bigger housing
后来后妈生了三个孩子
Then my stepmother gave birth to 3 children
一家六口
In a family of 6
家里天天吵个不停
there were fights at home every day
不知道是不是那时候我太小了
Maybe because I was too young
赚不到钱，帮不了家里
I couldn't make any money to help them
他们就把我赶了出来
so they kicked me out
其实我这辈子的愿望就是 要找到我的亲妈
The hope of my life is to find my natural mother
我爸爸只会骂我
My Dad scolded me...
这也不对、那也不对
forthis and that
我始终没叫他帮我找我妈
So I didn't ask his help to look for my mom at all
后来我…后来我跟了老大
Later on I... later on I found myself a chief
但他们…
But they...
他们说…只是去抢劫
They just said to rob
有意思…
Why not...
还想走
Come back here!
走？
Still want to run?
按著她！
Hold her down!
不如打电话勒索她家吧
Why don't we phone her home for blackmail?
电话号码呀？三八！
Phone number? Bitch!
放我走！放我们走呀！
Please let me go! Let us go
你说什么？
What are you saying?
电话号码英文怎么说？
What's phone number in English?
你们不知道吗？
You don't know?
我哪知道！
How should I know!
神经病！
Damn!
妈的！没电话号码怎能勒索？
Shit! How can we blackmail them without the phone number?
全都是饭桶！
All useless shit!
来，有便宜要占！
Come on! Might as well!
怎么搞的？你怎会按不住她的？
What the hell! Why can't you hold her down?
他们会认出我们的
They two will recognise us
打死他！
Kill him!
来！拿着，打他！
Come on! Hold this, beat him!
妈的！来呀！
Shit! Come on!
警告你们，人人有份，都得打几下
I'm warning you, no one can stay out of this
谁要不动手，我就打死他
I'll kill whoever doesn't beat them
过来，拿着！打他，打他呀
Come on, hold this! Hit him, hit him!
没想到会在宝马山闹出了命案
I didn't expect Braemar Hill to cost lives
你呢？十二年前你干了什么？
What about you? What did you do 12 years ago?
很痒啊
Very itchy!
自摸三番，糊了
What an easy win!
什么，你看你女儿！
What? Look at your daughter!
你死丫头，你给我下来呀！
Damn you, get down!
死丫头，你表姨父你也搞…
You damned girl, you even seduced your own uncle...
妈…别再打了…
Mom... stop...
你死丫头，我没你这个女儿， 你给我滚！
Damn you, I don't want a daughter like you. Get out!
不要…
Don't...
我不要你这个死丫头，你给我滚
I don't want a daughter like you. Get out
让我先穿好衣服呀
Let me put my clothes back on first
你还想穿什么衣服？
You still need your clothes?
你给我滚，走啊
Get out, out!
妈…开门…开门呀…
Mom... open the door... open the door!
妈！别这样，让我进去吧
Mom! Don't be like that, let me in!
妈！
Mom...
所谓“臭坑出臭草”
Stinky grass only grows out of a stinky pot
由中国政府钦点的筹委
The Organising Committee appointed by the Chinese government...
再由这些筹委决定了四百人的推委
decided on the 400 members of the Election Committee
来来去去都是这些人提名我们的特首
It's always the same group of people nominating our Chief Executive
试问那些参选人的候选政纲…
May I ask how can candidates' election platforms...
怎么才能跳出中国政府规定的框框？
avoid the limitations determined by the Chinese government?
一句“臭坑出臭草”
His Stinky grass only grows out of a stinky pot
骂了整个立法局和身兼推委的议员
insulted both the Legislative Council and Councillors on the Election Committee
怎么解释？主席，请你定断
How do you solve this, Mr Chairman? Please determine
粱忠勤议员，你愿不愿意收回 你刚才说的话？
Councillor, do you wish to withdraw your statement?
我不会收回
No, I don't!
因为话已经说出来了，我不能收回
I've said it, I can't take it back
誉玲就是找了这个人帮我们
It's him who Yue-ling got for us.
如果你不收回的话，请你马上离开
If you won't, please leave immediately
今天不用再回来
And not to return today
这个“臭坑出臭草”行不行的？
Will this stinky pot work?
再臭也是个议员嘛！
No matter how stinky he is, he's still a Councillor
我们寄了那么多信，只有他肯帮我们
Among all the letters we sent, he's the only one willing to help
粱议员，犯人家属全来了
The prisoners' families are all here
请他们进来
Bring them in
进来吧！
Come in!
我来介绍一下，这位是粱议员
Let me introduce the Councillor, Mr Leung
我们全靠他的了
We all depend on him
大家好！        粱议员你好！
Hi, everyone! Hi, Councillor!
我们全靠你了，你一定要帮我
We all depend on you, you must help us
我一定会尽力帮忙的
I'll try my best.
这一张是等候发落的犯人名单
This is the list of detained prisoners
你们在家属一栏签个名就行了， 传给大家吧！
Sign your name in the Next of Kin box. Pass it over!
粱议员，你要帮帮我
Councillor, you must help me
我儿子和不认识的人打架
My son fought with someone he didn't know
一句“看什么” ， 结果便杀了人
Just because he said, What are you looking at me for? It cost some lives
我没钱为儿子打官司
I have no money for a lawsuit
法律援助署的律师说…
The Legal Aid lawyer said...
判等候发落，最多关十年罢了
It was a maximum of 10 years for detention at Her Majesty's pleasure
那我就叫他认谋杀罪算了
So ljust asked him to plead guilty
谁知道认了便不能上诉了
So he did and couldn't appeal
你说怎么办？
What should I do?
粱议员，我弟弟也是这样
My younger brother was like that too, Councillor
他十三岁就辍学了，在车行里当学徒
He quit school at 13, and became an apprentice in a garage
谁知天天碰到小混混，问他要钱
The street kids asked him for money every day
我看他总不交钱给家里就骂他
He didn't bring home any money, so I yelled at him
有一天他回车房拿锯子
One day, he went back to the garage for a saw,
是用来自卫的
which was for self-defence
谁知道…谁知道弄成这样！
Nobody expected it to turn out like this!
让我先说！我弟弟叫小发
Let me speak first! My younger brother is called Fatt
有一天他在吃宵夜
One evening he was having midnight snack
旁边的人盯著他，老是盯著他
Some people kept staring at him
他火了
He got agitated
人家那边凶得要命，人多势众
Those people were a gang and they were yelling
他就坐计程车走
He left in a taxi
可是在车上愈想愈气，结果就跑回去
and felt more and more agitated. So he returned...
冲进人家的厨房，拿了刀到处乱砍
forced his way into the kitchen, grabbed a chopper and swung it
事情不是我弟弟惹起来的
My young brother didn't start it
我们家的人脾气非常暴躁
My family members are all very hot tempered
我知道了以后，正好手上拿着钥匙， 就打了过去
When I learned about it, ljust grabbed my keys and hit him...
差点弄瞎了他！
and almost blinded him!
要知道我们住在木屋区
We live in a wooden shack district, you know
我老妈天天骂人
Mom scolds us everyday
老爸在五金店工作苦，回家就发脾气
Dad has a tough time working in a hardware store. So he loses his temper at home
爸，你看我多棒！
Look, Dad! Ain't I good?
一口就把药粉吃光了
I finished the powder in one mouthful
小忠真乖！
Good boy, Siu-chung!
爸，电影要开始了，还不走就迟到了！
Dad, come on! We'll be late forthe movie!
对不起，我还要去开会！
Sorry! I still have to go to a meeting
我回家是要拿点儿东西，不能陪你了！
ljust came home to pick something up, can't go with you!
明明说好的，现在又说开会，你骗人！
You promised and now you have to go to a meeting! You lied!
小忠！
Siu-chung!
不理你了！
Leave me alone!
小忠，你出来！
Come out, Siu-chung!
我要冷静一下
I want to calm down
秀仪，你陪小忠去看吧！
Why don't you go with him, Sau-yee?
儿子说看“给我一个爸” 是应该爸爸陪的
Our son said his Dad should go with him to watch Kolya
今天的会是很重要的
The meeting is very important
哪次你不是这么说？
What else is new?
我《妇女协会》的会就不重要？
So my Women's Association meeting is not important?
我早跟你说了，我今天要开会
I told you I had a meeting to attend today
你总说你有理想
You always say you were idealistic
光是你有，我就没有！
So only you are and I'm not!
将来你做了救世主，儿子却不认你了
Your son denies you when you become a Saviour
誉玲！
Yue-ling!
你做我的助手，不怕丢了工作吗？
Are you not worried about losing your job helping me here?
我把工作辞掉了
I quit
辞掉了？
You did?
是的！不用担心
Yes! Don't worry!
我一直都想做一点事
I always wanted to do something...
不为了钱，也不为了生活
not forthe sake of money or living
现在机会来了
Here is my chance
我明天陪你到赤柱（监狱）好不好？
Can I go with you to Stanley (prison) tomorrow?
今天有议员要来吗？
A Councillor is coming here today?
是的！机灵点
Yeah! Be smart!
粱议员，你好！
Hi, Councillor!
你好！
Hi!
我姓潘，是这里的辅导员
Poon, I'm an adviser here
你好！这是张誉玲小姐，我的助手
Hi! This is Miss Cheung Yue-ling, my assistant
你好！        你好！
Hi! Hi!
这里有六个HMP（等候英女皇发落） 犯人
I advise all 6 prisoners detained at
全是由我辅导的
Her Majesty's pleasure
现在已经安排了他们跟你见面了
They have arranged to meet with you
这边请！        谢谢你！
This way, please! Thank you!
张小姐，行了，今天有特别安排
It's OK, Miss Cheung, a special arrangement today
这边请！        谢谢！
This way, please! Thank you!
阿Sir，今天开放式？这样子来探访！
It's Open Day today, Sir? So many visitors!
人家是议员，不是你妈！
What we have here today is a Councillor, not your mom!
粱议员，张小姐
Councillor, Miss Cheung!
这是我以前所念课程拿到的文凭
Here are the diplomas I received forthe courses I studied
你们看一看！
Take a look!
我现在正念公开大学社会系的 一个函授课程
I'm now taking a correspondence course in Sociology at the Open University
对现在的年青人都有理论 和实践的认识
So I have both theoretical and practical knowledge fortoday's youngsters
现在监狱推荐我做了监狱社工， 去辅导所有犯人
I was recommended as the adviser here to advise all prisoners
还有青年中心也替我出过书
Also, a youth centre helped publish my books
我现在…现在只想做一件事
There's only one thing... I want to do now
我想知道究竟还要在这里困多久？
I want to know how much longer I have to be stuck here
我很想出去！
I really want to get out of here!
想以过来人的身份告诉所有年青人
I want to tell all the youngsters about my experience
千万别犯法！
Never violate the law
我很希望你们能帮我
I really wish you could help me
小铭，里边在拍教育电视吗？
Are they filming an educational TV program in there, Ming?
你是陈永发吧？        是的！
Are you Chan Wing-fatt? Yes!
有什么话要说？
What have you got to tell me?
据我所知，长囚会每两年 就复检我们的案子
As far as I know, the Long Term Detention Review Committee (LTDRC) reviews my case every 2 years
我们的档案又重又厚
My file is thick and heavy
他们找秘书看了这些档案
They get a secretary to go over my file,
写几句结论
write a conclusion,
复检委员就只凭这几句结论 决定我们的命运
and that is just how the Committee members determine my fate
根本不公正、不客观、不准确
Neither just, objective, nor accurate
这种官僚制度便决定了我们的命运
This is the bureaucratic system that determines ourfate
希望我刚才的一番话有效吧
I hope what I said was useful
我是教师
I'm a teacher
我发现他比我的学生还聪明
I discovered he's even smarterthan my students
另外，他们的法律知识比很多 立法局议员还多
Also their legal knowledge is more detailed than many Councillors'
那当然了！ 这是他们的切身问题
Certainly! That is what most concerns them
他们天天研究法律，讲人权、讲自由
They study law day and night, talk about human rights and freedom
但是却从来没想过受害人家属的感受
Yet they neverthink about what the victims' families feel
你们两个，进来！
Come in, you two!
那边
Go overthere
这是粱议员，这是张小姐
This is the Councillor, this is Miss Cheung
我是黄育
I'm Wong Yuk
我是张有铭        你好！
I'm Cheung Yau-ming Hi!
对不起，该这一份才对
Sorry! It should be this file
好的！
OK!
坐吧！
Sit!
粱议员，我能不能说几句？
Mr. Leung, may I say something?
当然可以！
By all means!
粱议员，我宁愿香港跟大陆一样
I'd rather Hong Kong was the same as the Mainland
为什么？
Why?
这样枪毙我就算了
So I can be shot once and for all,
我妈用不著每次来都哭
and my mom won't need to cry every visit
在这里会关押到什么时候！
I don't know how long I will be detained here
我现在没死是因为家里有妈妈
I stay alive simply because I have a mom at home
万一我妈有什么事的话
If something happened to her,
我会自杀的！
I'd commit suicide!
孩子们挺乖的
The kids are pretty well behaved
是啊！
Yes!
张有铭很少说话
Cheung Yau-ming rarely talked
他是那些等候发落的犯人之中…
He's the only one detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
唯一没亲人为他争取确定刑期的一个
who has no family to fight on his behalf for a defined term,
而且十几年来家里人也没来看过他
as his family has never come to visit in the past 10 years or so
我也曾经帮他找过他家里人
I once helped him to get in touch with his family
他很想找到他妈妈
He wants to look for his mom so badly too
但是找不到
But no luck!
宝马山双尸案，当年这案子 真的非常轰动
The Braemar Hill case really shook the whole society that year
新闻不停播放，报纸也登了不少
The news was on airfrom time to time, and newspaper reports
小铭说他是被逼犯罪的
Ming said he was forced to commit the crime
我相信他，当时他那么小，才十几岁
I believe him. He was so young, just a teenager
这些年来他那么努力读书
He's been studying very hard these years
就是想能早点出狱，重新做人
He plans to get out early and turn over a new leaf
你跟他非亲非故，为什么要帮助他？
Why do you want to help him? You are not related to him!
不知道！
Don't know!
可能小时候没人关心我
Probably because no one cared for me in my childhood
我很明白没人关心自己的感觉
I fully understand those feelings
我在木屋区长大
I grew up in a wooden shack district
那儿的环境很差
The environment was really bad there
人们用的电都是从路灯那儿偷来的
The power supply was stolen from the streetlights
很容易发生火灾
Fires occurred very easily
火灾发生就很难逃命
and it was very hard to escape
我妈带我从大陆来这儿
My mom brought me from the Mainland;
来了之后她完全变了
since then she changed completely
脾气很坏
She became very bad tempered,
天天怕这个、怕那个
and was afraid of this and that
那你呢，你为什么帮他们？
What about you? Why are you helping him?
欧洲人权法庭已裁定不定期 押后判刑是违法的
The European Human Rights Court ruled that indefinite detention is illegal
为什么要等女皇判决呢？
Why must there be at Her Majesty's pleasure?
乃因为案件特殊
Because in special cases,
不能由法庭和法官去判决
it is not forthe court and judge to set the sentence
该改由非司法机构或非司法人士来判决
The sentence is set by non-judiciary people or organisations
那就是说筹钱打官司也是没用的了？
In that case, there's no point in raising money for a lawsuit?
港督只有四个多月时间
The Governor only has about 4 months left here
这二十三个青少年犯是殖民地 法律制造出来的
These 23 young offenders were created by colonial law
殖民政府撤离香港前有责任解决这件事
The colonial government must deal with them before leaving
万一回归前…
What if the Hong Kong-British government...
港英政府没裁定明确刑期，那怎么办？
hasn't determined the sentence before the Handover?
根据基本法第四十八条
According to article 48 of the basic law,
特区行政长官有权赦免任何犯人
the Chief Executive of the SAR has the right to grant amnesty
但是回归后“等候英女皇发落”的裁决
But Detained at Her Majesty's pleasure might change to...
可能就会改为等候特首发落 之类的判刑吧！
Detained at the Chief Executive's pleasure afterthe Handover,
就是说变相重复裁决同一罪名
which means double jeopardy forthe same crime
是不符合人权法的！
That is against the human rights law!
粱先生！我来这儿开会，看到你太好了
Mr. Leung! I came here to consult, it's so nice to bump into you
你太太催你签离婚书
Your wife urges you to sign the divorce papers
你告诉她，我不签！
Tell her I won't!
谁啊？小忠？什么事啊？
Who is it? Siu-chung? What's the matter?
你生日我记著了！
I rememberyour birthday!
不过你生日那天爸要开会
But I have to go to a meeting on your birthday
改天我买个大冰淇淋蛋糕给你好吗？
I'll buy you a big ice cream cake sometime, OK?
别生气了，好吧？拜拜！
Don't get upset! All right? Bye!
妈咪，我来帮你好吗？
Mom, may I help?
小忠，小心！别把妈咪的东西弄脏
Be careful, Siu-chung, don't dirty Mom's things
听话，自己玩去！别碍著妈做事好吗？
Be a good boy, go play yourself, OK? Mom's busy
乖，快去！
Come on, go!
对…记得！今天开会，是的， 我会准时到的time
Yeah... I remember! We have a meeting today. Yes! I'll be there on time
你把人找齐，把文件准备好，对…
You go collect everyone, and get the papers ready. Right!
爸…今天是星期日， 你陪我出去玩啊！
Dad! Lt's Sunday today, go play with me!
我一会儿再跟你说，就这样吧，拜拜！
I'll call you back, OK! Bye!
爸今天要开会，不能陪你了
Dad has to go to a meeting today, and can't play with you
下星期好吗？
How about next week?
你怎么这样子？将来妈咪跟你 离婚之后，我才不跟你
How can you do this to me? I won't go with you when Mom divorces you
你为什么跟儿子说这些话？
Why did you tell our son things like this?
怎么？儿子无权知道我们之间的事吗？
Why not? Hasn't our son the right to know what's happening between us?
我们之间有什么事？
What is happening between us?
我尊重你做的事，你也要尊重我， 对不对？
I respect what you do, and so you must respect me too, right?
说来说去都是那一套，我懒得理你
I can't be bothered, you just keep saying the same thing
我要赶去中环示威呀！
I must rush to Central for a demonstration!
你照顾一下儿子吧，别去示威了， 好吗？
Why don't you spend some time with our son? Don't go, will you?
你说什么？
What are you talking about?
我最近见了二十几个青少年犯
I've met about 20 young prisoners lately
我有点害怕呀！
I'm really worried!
怕就好了，儿子没你份的吗？
Good foryou! Isn't he your son too?
小忠！
Siu-chung!
妈咪要去做事，听爸的话，知道吗？
Mom has some work to do. Do what Dad will ask you to, all right?
知道了！
All right!
妈咪拜拜
Bye, Mom!
小忠！
Siu-chung!
干什么？
What?
跟爸去开会好吗？
Will you go with me to the meeting?
不去！
No!
开完会我请你吃饭
We'll eat out afterthe meeting
我要吃牛扒跟香蕉船！
I want steak and a banana split!
你想吃什么都行
Whateveryou want
但是先要吃药，你吃了没有？
But you must take your medicine first. Have you?
吃了！
Yes!
吃了？
You have?
小忠你出来！爸有话问你
Get out, Siu-chung! I want to ask you something
你明明没吃，为什么说吃了？
You haven't taken it; why did you say you had?
说谎是不对的，你知道吗？
Lying is wrong, you know that?
把手拿出来
Put your hand out
爸打你，你生爸的气吗？
Dad hit you. Are you mad at me?
你还疼不疼爸？
Do you still love Dad?
Do you?
你不说话…
You're silent...
就是说你不疼爸了，对吗？
means you don't, right?
对！
Right!
你为什么不疼爸？
Why?
你从来不陪我
You never spend time with me
最近很多人需要爸帮忙
Many people need Dad's help lately
我答应你，我帮完他们以后…
When I finish helping them, I promise...
我天天陪你上街好吗？
I'll take you out every day, OK?
对不起！你代我签吧！
I'm sorry, can you sign for me? I'm illiteracy
你们先吃啊！
You go ahead!
请结帐！
The bill, please!
走了？再坐一会儿嘛！
Are you going? Stay for a while!
各位，我跟保安司谈过
Gentlemen, I've talked to the Secretary for Security
他说等候英女皇发落的犯人…
He said prisoners who are detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
要留给将来特区政府的行政长官处理
are to be managed by the Chief Executive of the SAR
我早说英国人是靠不住的了！
I told you the British were unreliable
我都说他们在推卸责任的了！
As I said, they are disregarding their responsibilities
回归以后，公安随时会抓那些人 去枪毙的
The police will shoot the kids any time afterthe Handover
怎…么…办呢我儿子…？
What will happen to my son?
求求你！救救我儿子！
I beg you! Save my son!
婆婆你别哭了！
Don't cry, Madam! You make me feel lost
我们要去港督府抗议
We want to have a demonstration at the Governor's House
抗议是需要的
A demonstration is necessary
但是你要明白，我们现在为重犯请愿
But you must understand that we are now appealing for serious offenders
不仅是挑战官僚架构
Not only are we challenging the bureaucratic structure,
走到街上去就是挑战整个社会 对囚犯憎恨的态度
but we're also challenging society's resentful attitude towards prisoners
如果我们想成功，你们就一定 要坚持到底
So if we want success, you must be persistent to the end
我们马上搞一个街头签名运动
We'll organise a signature campaign on the street
签名收集够了就递交港督
When enough signatures are collected, we'll submit them to the Governor
那可不行，我不能让别人知道 我儿子在坐牢
No! I can't let people know my son is in jail
我也不行，我跟别人说儿子在深圳 做生意罢了！
Me neither! I told people my son runs a business in Shenzhen
香港四分之一的家庭都有人坐牢
A quarter of Hong Kong families have members in jail
我们站出来的话，也许有人会 同情我们的
If we stand out, we might gain sympathy
可是很多人都像我从前那样
The thing is,
装著很憎恨犯罪的人
many people pretend to hate criminals like us
好让人家以为自己跟犯人没关系嘛！
So that others think they have nothing to do with criminals
要是记者在我脸上打格子，那我就答应
I'll do it only if reporters conceal my face
如果怕被别人认出来
If you're worried people will recognise you,
那你们戴帽子好了、戴墨镜好了、 蒙著脸也可以
wear a hat, sunglasses, or coveryourface
但是示威游行的人一定要多， 一定要够
But many people must participate in the demonstration. We must have enough
婆婆，你那么爱哭， 不如对著记者哭吧！
You enjoy crying so much! Why don't you cry in front of the reporters?
惠珍，这次的请愿行动， 由你负责联络家属
Take charge of liaison with the families forthe demonstration, Wai-chun!
好啊！
OK!
我也去查一下资料， 看对他们有帮助没有！
I'll go check the information to see if it's any help
谢谢你！
Thank you!
站住…
Stop...
帮忙抓住她…
Hold her down...
救命啊…放我走！
Help... Let me go.
抓住她的手…    干什么？
Grab her hands! What are you doing?
抓住她…
Grab her hands!
天！
Oh my God...
张开她的腿！
Open her legs!
抓著她的手！
Grab her hands!
别吵呀，死老外！
Stop yelling, jerk!
杀害我儿子和他女朋友的人该被判死刑
Whoever did this to my son and his girlfriend deserve a death penalty.
他们的行为连禽兽都不如
They'd be put to death, they're animals, they shouldn't be walking around!
快出发了，怎么誉玲还没来？
We're going soon, why isn't Yue-ling here?
不知道！打电话给她也没人听
Don't know! I called her and there was no answer
不等她了，我们出发吧！
We are not waiting for her, let's go!
小心别涂错！
Be careful, don't get it wrong!
这里好像还欠一点儿！
It doesn't seem OK here!
要很鲜艳的
Make it more colourful
小铭，书上这个May day， 是什么意思？
What does May day here in the picture mean, Ming?
不是May day ，是Mayday
It's not May day, it's Mayday
如果你在海上遇险，要求救， 是救命的意思
If you are in danger at sea and need help. It means Help!
Mayday     救命救命的意思
Mayday means help
这个管用呀！
This is useful!
Mayday      我们也要求救呀
Right! We need mayday
现在是本港新闻
Now, the local news
立法局议员粱忠勤…
Legislative Councillor Leung Chung-ken...
今天陪同多名仍然等候英女皇 发落的犯人家属…
went with many families of prisoners detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
由铜锣湾轩尼斯道游行至港督府…
to march from Hennessey Rd in Causeway Bay to the Governor's House
为青少年犯争取确定刑期
demanding determination of juvenile offenders' sentences
英国人应当承担责任！
Britain is responsible!
青少年犯也有人权！
Juvenile offenders have rights too!
人权不容践踏！
Human rights are not to be stepped on!
英国人应当承担责任！
Britain is responsible!
青少年犯也有人权！
Juvenile offenders have rights too!
争取马上确定刑期！
Fight for immediate determination of sentence!
青少年犯不是垃圾！
Juvenile offenders are not trash!
人权不容践踏！
Human rights are not to be stepped on!
争取马上确定刑期！
Fight for immediate determination of sentence!
阿勤，留点儿时间给我们吧！
Save some time for us, Ken!
搞这种犯人的案子，吃力不讨好
Dealing with criminals of this kind will get you nowhere
粱忠勤，保安司说什么就什么嘛
Do whateverthe Secretary for Security says, Ken!
还搞那么多事干什么？
Why bothers doing all this?
快下车（不能过渡回归的议员）了， 那么多事要做
We're off the train soon (replaced afterthe Handover). We've much to do!
其实我们每个都收过那些信
In fact, we all received letters like that
犯人总喜欢叫人帮他们减刑的！
Prisoners always want people help to reduce their sentences
我们又不是法官
We are not judges,
何况香港60％的市民都赞成死刑
and 60% of Hong Kong people want the death penalty
你帮重犯说话似乎不很符合民意哪！
You're siding with serious criminals; it doesn't go with public opinion
为何为了二十几个人而 开罪三百万选民呢？
Why irritate 3 million voters for the sake of about 20 people?
我明白你的意思
I understand what you're saying
但我始终想做我认为对的事
But I still want to do what I think is right
各位市民，一群曾经被法庭判为
Fellow citizens, a group of juvenile offenders,
“等候英女皇发落”的青少年犯
who the court sentenced to be detained at Her Majesty's pleasure,
现在要求香港政府本著人道及人权立场
ask the HK Government to determine their sentences as soon as possible...
尽快给他们明确的刑期
from humanitarian and human rights standpoints
好让他们可以计划未来，重新投入社会
So that they can plan theirfutures and re-enter society
请各位市民过来签名，支持他们
Please come and sign your name to support them,
使他们早日得到刑期，谢谢大家！
to enable their sentences to be determined as soon as possible.
“请各位市民过来签名，支持他们，“
Please come and sign your name to support them,
尽快给他们明确的刑期
to enable their sentences to be determined as soon as possible
使他们能够准备未来，重新融于社会
to enable them to prepare forthe future and re-enter society
请各位市民过来签名
Please come and sign your name
粱议员，我是你的支持者
Councillor, I support you
谢谢…
Thank you...
我什么都支持你
I support you in everything you do
但是帮杀人犯我就不支持了
But not when you support murderers
先生，你有所不知！
You don't understand, Mister!
那些青少年犯罪的时候
Those teenagers were not mature...
心智还未成熟，不很清楚 自己在干什么！
when they committed crimes. They didn't know what they were doing
何况现在他们在牢里无了期地等
It's torture forthem...
是很磨人的事
to wait endlessly in jail
最可怜的是由于他们没有确定刑期
The worst is, they can't appeal...
根本没有办法上诉
without determined sentences
对他们很不公平！
It's extremely unfain'to them!
粱议员，你这是什么议员？
What kind of Councillor are you?
最近一群青年放火烧掉一间卡拉OK， 死了很多人
Recently some kids set fire to a karaoke bar and many people died
你怎能放那些青少年犯呢？
How can you set those juvenile offenders free?
我们曾经给政府写过很多信
I sent many letters to the Government...
询问有关等候英女皇发落的青少年犯
to ask if the young offenders who are detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
到底他们能否在主权移交前 得到合理刑期
could have their sentences determined before the Handover
但政府总在打官腔
But the government always gave bureaucratic answers
很多信写了去政府那里
Many letters have been sent to the government
呸！
Shit!
你做什么？
What are you doing?
你做什么？别捣乱！
What are you doing? Stop fooling around!
你是什么人？
Who are you?
什么人都不关你事！
None of your business!
别打了…
Stop!
停手！
Stop... calm down...
根据最新的社会调查指出
According to the latest social survey...
香港有42％中学生认为没有人 可以说心里话
42% of high school students have nobody to discuss their problems
34％的中学生认为父母不了解他们…
34% of those whose parents don't understand them...
你们吵什么？坐一边去吧， 我还要做生意呢！
Move aside! I have business to do!
要不是你拦著我，我一定揍那混蛋
I would give him a good lesson if you didn't stop me
我实在忍无可忍了，你们两怎么搞的？
I can't stand you people anymore, what did you think you were doing?
我们在和平请愿示威， 你两却在跟人打架？
We were having a peaceful demonstration, and you two fought?
你们有没有想过市民会怎看我们？
Did you ever care about how people would look at us?
对不起！我不该那么大声的
I'm sorry, I shouldn't have raised my voice
不过我真想告诉你们
But I'm telling you,
你们真的很不对！
you were very wrong!
粱先生，你根本不用说对不起， 是他们不对！
Mr. Leung, you don't need to say sorry. They were wrong!
粱议员和我们非亲非故
Mr. Leung isn't related to us at all
他没义务帮我们的
He has no obligation to help us
上次游行我的样子见了报以后， 人人就怕了我们！
My picture was in the news in the last demonstration. Now they stay away!
我只要嗓门大了点儿
It was just that my voice was a bit loud
你们看！这厨子立即就把菜刀 牛肉刀都收起来了
Look at this chef! He hid his choppers right away
所以我们一定要克制自己
So we must restrain ourselves
要不然就救不了家里人了！
Otherwise we won't be able to save ourfamilies
算了！惠珍，别动气了！
It's OK, Wai-chun! Don't lose your cool
找到誉玲了吗？
Have you located Yue-ling?
没有！我打了很多电话给她， 都没人听
No! I called her many times, there was no answer
爸爸就会骂我
Dad scolded me
到了最后，我也没有找他帮我
I didn't ask him to help after all
为什么打这小孩呢？
Why are you beating this boy?
我教儿子关你什么事？
I'm teaching my son a lesson. What has it got to do with you?
不是这样教儿子的！
That's no way to treat your son!
你这样打他，他将来会坐牢的
If you beat him like that, he'll go to jail in the future
坐牢也不关你的事！
His going to jail has nothing to do with you either!
不听话…     我不敢了…
Don't you dare not to listen to me... I won't dare any more
别再打了，他是你儿子，你知道吗？
Stop! He's your son, don't you know?
什么事？
What's going on?
阿Sir，他打他儿子！
Sir, he's beating his son!
为什么打孩子？
Why?
我教我儿子
I was teaching my son a lesson
教儿子也不能打，你还绑著他？
That's not an excuse. You tied him up?
快放了他，不然告你虐待儿童
Let him go or I'll press charges against you for child abuse
很久没见了！
Long time no see!
你好！
Hi!
你弄伤了手？
Your hand's injured?
是的！
Yes!
没事吧？
Are you OK?
粱先生说你病了，我很担心
Mr. Leung said you were sick, I was worrying about you
我看你那么久没来， 还以为你出了什么事
You haven't come for a long time, I thought something happened to you
你为我做了那么多的事
You have done so much for me
这次你病了，我都不能出去看你
You were sick, and I couldn't even pay you a visit
求求你，让我进去！我还想再看看他
Please let me go back in, I still want to see him!
不行，出来了就不能再进去！
No! You can't go back in once you've come out!
下星期再来好了！
Come again next week!
小铭！
Ming!
别叫了！
Stop shouting!
对不起！
Sorry!
粱先生，影印机又坏了
Mr. Leung, the photocopier has broken down again
明天找人来修一下吧！
Get someone to fix it tomorrow!
粱先生，如果再做犯人案子的话 我想辞职了
Mr. Leung, I'll resign if we continue with the criminals' case
我的亲戚朋友知道我帮犯人做事 都在说我的不是！
My relatives gossiped about me when they learned I work for criminals!
对啊！再说，也快回归了
Yeah! The Handover is coming,
到时候你也没议员当了
by then you won't be a Councillor anymore
不如多做一点反对临时立法会的事 不是更好吗？
Won't it be better if we work against the provisional Legislative Council?
何况犯人是没有投票权的！
Offenders have no right to vote anyway!
你们两个干什么？
What are you two doing?
那些英国人把小孩像垃圾 一样的扔在一边
Those British throw these kids aside like trash
那是对的吗？那没违反人权吗？
Is it right? Doesn't it violate human rights?
做事不能光计较后果，该做的就要做！
You can't calculate the result, you should do what you must do!
你回来干什么？
What are you doing here?
我们最缺人的时候你就不见了
You disappeared when we needed helping hands the most
没有你我照样会帮他们的
I will still help them without you
看了宝马山命案的资料后，我很害怕
I was very afraid after reading about the Braemar Hill case
你不是早就知道自己在帮什么人的吗？
Didn't you know what people you were helping in the first place?
色彩强一点
Use stronger colour
色彩多一点
More colourful!
青少年犯不是垃圾！
Juvenile offenders are not trash!
争取马上确定刑期！
Fight for immediate and specific sentences
青少年犯也有人权！
Juvenile offenders have rights too!
小铭，对不起！
I'm sorry, Ming!
我曾经想放弃你，不再帮你了
I once thought of giving you up, not helping you any more
请你原谅我！
Please forgive me!
当我看到宝马山双尸案的资料的时候
When I read about the case of the Braemar Hill couple
我真的很害怕
I was really frightened
我不相信在我眼前的你
I can't believe the person I see now...
曾经做过那么凶残的事
did such a brutal thing
其实我比你也好不了多少
Actually, I'm no betterthan you
我也是一个犯过罪的人
I once committed a crime too
十二年前，我想杀了我的表姨母
I wanted to kill my Aunt 12 years ago
只是我没被人抓到
Only I was not arrested
所以现在还能自由自在的到处去
So I'm still free to go anywhere
虽然我知道没借口可以掩饰我们 曾经犯过的罪
Although I realise there is no excuse for our crimes,
但是我又很明白你童年时 所受过的伤害
I fully understand your childhood suffering
小铭，我不知道你会怎么想
I don't know what's in your mind, Ming
但是我觉得纵使时光可以倒流
But I feel that if we could go back into the past,
我也不想再来一次
I wouldn't want it to happen to me again
因为我怕自己会再犯同样的错
Because I'm afraid I would still make the same mistake
要求尽早确定刑期！
We demand specific sentences as soon as possible!
青少年犯也有人权！
Juvenile offenders have rights too!
要求尽早确定刑期！
We demand specific sentences as soon as possible!
反对无了期监禁！
We object to endless imprisonment!
要求尽早确定刑期！
We demand specific sentences as soon as possible!
反对无了期监禁！
We object to endless imprisonment!
青少年犯也有人权！
Juvenile offenders have rights too!
反对无了期监禁！
We object to endless imprisonment!
要求尽早确定刑期！
We demand specific sentences as soon as possible!
等一下，粱议员有话要说
Wait! Mr. Leung has something to say
各位，任何触犯法律的人
Ladies and gentlemen, anyone who violates the law...
都该受到合理的惩罚
should receive reasonable punishment
但是今天我们的香港
But nowadays in Hong Kong,
我们高度强调法治和人权
we emphasise law and order, and human rights
却竟然忽略了二十三个等候英女皇 发落的青少年犯
Yet we have ignored 23 young criminals detained at Her Majesty's pleasure,
无限期地监禁他们
and imprisoned them indefinitely
粱议员，这里的一些剪报都 是跟问题青少年有关的
All these newspaper clippings are about juvenile delinquents
你认为值得帮助这些问题青少年吗？
Do you think they are worth helping?
我个人认为问题青少年是 问题社会的产物
I personally think that juvenile offenders are products of a sick society
我们老说青少年这不好、那不好
We keep saying that teenagers are bad in this orthat way
追求名牌、挥霍无度、乱搞男女关系
They are vain, waste money, and have sex all the time
但是有很多成年人可能忘了…
But probably many adults might have forgotten that
我们也曾经历过心智不成熟的成长阶段
we went through these immature stages while growing up too
我们一方面埋怨一代不如一代、 青少年愈来愈不长进
On one side we complain about teenagers become more and more careless
但是另方面却在制造一个堕落的世界
But on the other, we are creating a world of corruption...
引诱青少年做坏事
to seduce teenagers into bad ways
我觉得这样很不公平，也很荒谬
I find this ridiculous and very unfair
立法会主席赶你走的时候 干么你不坚持呢？
Why didn't you insist when the LegCo Chairman expelled you, Mr. Leung?
你认为“臭坑出臭草” 这句话有问题吗？
Was your phrase Stinky grass only comes from a stinky pot problematic?
在殖民议会上
You were the first one on record who got chased out...
你开创了第一次指出不民主选举 而被赶离场的纪录
after pointing out the undemocratic election at a colonial meeting
你该为自己的勇气而骄傲， 坚持不离场的
You should have been proud of yourself and insisted on staying
为什么主席叫你走，你就走？
Why did you do what the Chairman said?
我觉得今天不是讨论这问题的适当时候
I don't think it's appropriate to discuss this mattertoday
港督彭定康复核了二十三名 被判等候英女皇发落…
Governor Patten reviewed the 23 cases detained at Her Majesty's pleasure...
而仍然未确定刑期的犯人个案后
yet they still haven't been given specific sentences
决定释放四名被押刑期过长的囚犯
and he decided to free 4 who had been jailed fortoo long
又为两名被押超过十五年的 犯人确定刑期
He also confirmed the sentences of 2 who had been jailed for over 15 years
其余的个案就交给将来的特区政府处理
The rest of the cases are to be handed over to the SAR government
谢谢你，粱先生，我终于得到了 二十六年的刑期
Thank you, Mr. Leung! I finally got confirmation of 26 years' imprisonment
不必客气！
You're welcome!
二十六年！刑期比成年犯还重
26 years! The sentence is even longerthan for adult criminals
他有了刑期就可以申请假释
He can apply for parole now
扣除假期，再捱一个多月， 就可以放出去了
After holidays, he can be out in a month
不对呀！这样就是说…
This is not right! That means...
政付被迫要判重一点儿
the government was forced to decide on longer sentences
如果轻判了，关久了不知道
If not, then if someone was already jailed for longerthan he should be,
那白关了的日子怎样赔？
how could the government pay him back?
也好，有刑期代表有希望
It's good, with a given sentence, there is hope
我们二十三个人争取确定刑期
23 of us fought for determination of sentence
彭定康只是处理了五个赤柱 （监狱）的案子
And Chris Patten only settled 5 of the Stanley (Prison) cases
石壁（监狱）这边，只有国良
Over here in Shek Pik (Prison), only Kwok-leung got it
剩下我们十七个怎么办呢？
What about the 17 of us?
彭定康是一个政客
Chris Patten is a politician
你要十分，通常他只会给你三分
You want 10, usually he'll just give you 3
回归前我会尽最大的努力
I'll try my very best before the Handover
我会尽量帮你们的
I'll help the best I can
犯人也有人权！
Prisoners have human rights too!
人权不容践踏！
Human rights are not to be stepped on!
立即确定刑期！
Determine the sentences immediately!
香江电台记者何慕诗现在 还继续在立法局…
Ho Mo See of Radio Television Heung Kong now continues her report...
现场报导回归前最后一次 立法局会议的情况
on the last meeting before the Handover, outside the Legislative Council
怎么还没提到我们
Why didn't they mention about us?
到现在为止，会议已经开了 超过十个小时s
So far, the meeting has been going on for over 10 hours
现场所见，多位议员都开始有疲态
Many Council members at the meeting are beginning to look tired
在立法会门外，有多个团体静坐抗议
Many groups are holding sit-in protests outside the Council
他们认为临时立法会是非法的
They think the Provisional Legislative Council is illegal
在休息之前，议员刚刚辩论完 香烟条例草案
Council members have just finished a debate on the tobacco bill... before the break
阿发，什么时候才会轮到我们？
When will it be ourturn, Fatt?
我哪儿知道！
How should I know?
就算轮到，你们也不是马上就可以走的！
Even so, you people won't be free in the next second!
跟著是辩论保安科所提交的长期 监禁刑罚覆检条例草案
Next is the Security Branch review of the long-term imprisonment bill
主席，各位议员
Chairman, fellow Councillors
首先，为提供一个刑期复检…
First of all, in orderto provide a sentence review...
说到我们了，大家安静
It's ourturn! Quiet, everyone!
我们建议把原来长期囚禁覆检委员会
We suggest confirming the LTDRC...
确立为法定机构
as a legal organisation
基于等候英女皇发落 这项判决的性质和目的
Due to the nature and purpose of detained at Her Majesty's pleasure,
裁决为酌情终身监禁
The verdict is now discretionary life sentence
等候英女皇发落和酌情终身
We can't equate detained at Her Majesty's pleasure and discretionary life sentence...
此两事根本不能相提并论
because they are two totally different things
“酌情终身”本来就有终身的含意
Discretionary life sentence virtually means a life term
但是“等候英女皇发落” 却只是等待发落
But detained at Her Majesty's pleasure is just waiting to be sentenced
等待一种宽大的刑罚
Waiting for a generous penalty...
绝对没有终身的含意
absolutely does not imply a life term
如果未满十八岁的青少年
If teenagers under 18...
也受到同样有终身含意的刑罚
also sufferthe penalty of an implied life term,
那青少年犯和成年犯到底有什么分别？
then how does a juvenile offender differfrom an adult criminal?
法庭一直都把十八岁以下 该判死刑的犯人
Criminals under 18 with the death penalty...
判为等候英女皇发落
were detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
很明显是不想把青少年犯和成年犯 用同一方法处理
Obviously young offenders should not be handled the same way as adults
再说，就算是成年犯判了死刑
Even if an adult is sentenced to death,
港督亦例必改判为终身监禁
the Governor always changes it to life
如果现在把等候英女皇发落 等同酌情终身的话
If we now equate detained at Her Majesty's pleasure with discretionary sentence for life,
我们岂不是兜了个大圈子？
don't we just go back to where we started?
为什么要这么做呢？
Why are we doing this?
你们是不是要将青少年犯心智不成熟
Do you want to ignore the very reason of...
这个那么值得考虑的因素一笔勾销？
young criminals' immaturity, which is so much worth considering?
请大家看看你们面前的那份犯罪记录
Please take a look at the criminal record in front you
囚犯编号四七六二八
The prisoner's number is 47628
长囚会在一九九二年一月复检他的案子
The LTDRC reviewed his case in January, 1992
他犯罪的时候只有十五岁
He was only 15 when the crime was committed
以前没有任何犯罪记录
Before that he was clean
长囚会对他在监狱工作的表现 和学业成绩…
The LTDRC complimented...
都有很高的评价
his studies and his performance in jail
长囚会鼓励他继续发奋图强和改过自新
They encouraged him to keep working hard and make a new life
但是一直到今天
But up to today,
他仍然没有一个确定的刑期
he still hasn't had his sentence determined
试问他怎样发奋图强、怎样改过自新？
How can he keep working hard and make a new life?
我们这个所谓文明社会
How can our so-called civil society...
竟可那么不人道地继续监禁一个 想改过的年青人！
continue to jail a youngster who wants to correct himself like that?
这公平吗？
Is it fair?
你们所谓的酌情终身
Your so-called discretionary life sentence...
其实只是一个逃避责任、明哲保身
is just an excuse to avoid responsibility, to keep your hands clean
和无限期监禁他的一个籍口
and leaving him to indefinite imprisonment
一九九三年四月
In April, 1993,
立法局修改法例，废除死刑
the Legislative Council amended the law to repeal the death penalty
任何年龄的人只要谋杀罪名成立
Anybody of any age, as long as he is guilty of homicide,
就一律被判终身监禁
will be sentence for life
现在这条草案，是根据法理和法律 程序起草的
Now that this bill has been drafted, based on legal procedures and processes
绝对没有忽视人道精神
The humane spirit has absolutely not been ignored
对于危害社会的杀人犯来说
As for murderers who harm society,
“酌情终身”已经是最人道的判决
discretionary life sentence is the most humane sentence
法律有责任保护社会
The Law has the responsibility of protecting society
我们绝不能轻易放过危害社会的杀人犯
We can't easily let go of them
虽然我们已经废除了死刑
Although we repealed the death penalty
但是在你们心目中
But in your heart,
“杀人偿命”这观念仍然根深蒂固
the view of A life for a life is still deeply held
如果真是这样，我想奉劝一句
If this is really the case, let me give you a piece of advice
我们这个铁面无私和公正严明的政府
That our government of justice and principle,
还有我们这群尊贵的议员
as well as our noble Councillors,
不要再玩把戏，不要再愚弄那群孩子了
stop playing tricks and stop fooling those boys
什么玩把戏？
What trick?
律政司已经把长囚会界定为法律机构了
The Attorney General already made the LTDRC a legal organisation
这不是改进吗？我们没必要 在这问题上浪费时间
Isn't this progress? We shouldn't waste any more time on this issue
我觉得我们没有浪费时间
I don't think so
如果“等候英女皇发落”
If detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
被理解为“酌情终身监禁”的话
is understood as discretionary life sentence
那不仅在法律应用上是错误的
It is not only wrong in terms of legal usage,
后果也非常严重
but the result is also very serious
当年，根据刑事诉讼条例第七十条
That year, according to the Criminal Procedure Ordinance, Article 70
由于法官不能判青少年重犯死刑
since the judge couldn't sentence young criminals to death,
所以才判为等候英女皇发落
he sentenced them to be detained at Her Majesty's pleasure
这里还有一个个案
Here's another case
成年犯五八三零四犯了杀人罪， 法庭判了他死刑
An adult criminal 58304 committed murder, and was sentenced to death
长囚会建议他改判终身
The LTDRC recommended life imprisonment
后来便改判为三十年
Later his sentence was changed to 30 years
此人入狱后又杀人，又判死刑
He committed murder again in jail, and was sentenced to death again
长囚会又建议改判他三十四年
And the LTDRC again recommended a sentence of 34 years
扣除了假期，他实际上 只需坐二十二年牢
After deducting holidays, he's actually required to spend 22 years in jail
但是我们的小孩已经坐了十几年
But the boys have already been jailed for more than ten years...
现在换来的只是“酌情终身监禁”
and are just in exchange for discretionary life sentence
这是什么逻辑？！
What kind of logic is this?
法治社会讲求理性
A society of law and order demands rationality
绝不能因为一个人感情用事 而伤害整个社会
That cannot be harmed simply because someone becomes emotional
理性？你那些只是麻木不仁的理性
Rationality? What you said was an unfeeling kind of rationality
你们只说惩罚、惩罚、再惩罚
What you all say is just penalty, penalty, still penalty
惩罚可以解决所有问题吗？
Can penalties solve all problems?
我们现在不是在清洁香港
We are not cleaning up Hong Kong now
不能把我们看成是垃圾的 东西扔在一边
We can't just put something we considertrash aside...
就以为能解决一切问题了
and expect all problems to be solved
粱忠勤，你没头没脑的 风头出够了没有？
Haven't you attracted enough attention, Leung Chung-ken?
保安司的条例虽然不太好
Although the Security Branch ordinances are not so great,
但总比没有的好
they are betterthan none
政府这次也算不错的了， 肯马上起草草案回应你
The government did well this time by drafting the bill immediately
通过就算了
Just accept what we passed
我们还有十多小时便要下车了
We won't be Councillors anymore in 10 hours or so
难道你放心把这条草案交给 临时立法会处理吗？
Are you comfortable handing this bill to provisional Legislative Council?
由保安科提议的长期监禁 刑罚复检条例草案
After all Councillors voted,
经议员投票后已有了结果
the result of the Security Branch Life Term Review Bill has come out
立法局以多数票通过了 由保安科提案的…
The Life Term Sentence Review Bill suggested by the Secretary Branch...
长期监禁刑罚复检条例草案
were passed in the Legislative Council by a majority vote
并否决了粱议员的六项修订动议
And the 6 amendments moved by Councillor Leung Chung-ken were vetoed
犯人也有人权！
Prisoners have rights too!
人权不能践踏！
Human rights are not to be stepped on!
立即确定刑期！
Determine the sentences immediately!
人权不容践踏！
Human rights are not to be stepped on!
立即确定刑期！
Determine the sentences immediately!
悲秋风 香江梦 家乡一切幻变中
The wind of autumn sobs over Hong Kong's dream. Everything is changing at home
满腔热血失青春 各散西东命难同
I lost my youth to my ardent faith. Ourfates differ as we part for separate destinations
青年两代送 历劫半生命犹穷
Two generations pass, half a lifetime goes, yet nothing is gained
秋来更思痛 谢了春花变残红
Recalling the painful past in autumn, spring flowers wither, tarnished red
本人董建华…
I, Tung Chee Wah...
悲秋风 香江玫瑰梦 抚今追昔难舍中
Sobbing in the wind of autumn over Hong Kong's dream. Remembering the past, and it is difficult to forget
那堪梦觉一朝空 难料沧桑别后容
Nothing is left on awaking from the dream. I can't imagine how my home will look after all the hardships
国家之情已伤痛 盼顾香江又重逢
The feelings of our country are painful. Here I see Hong Kong again
飘零四海送 落拓他乡似条虫
We wander around abandoned in another country like lost leaves
我们一定会重返立法会
We will return to the Legislative Council
好…
Yes...
大家先听我说，我们一定会回来
Say with me! We will return
我们一定会回来
We will return
我们一定重返立法会
We will return to the Legislative Council
我们作为中国的一部分
We, as part of China,
已经开始了一个民主奋斗的旅程
have already started the journey of fighting for democracy
这个旅程不是容易的，是艰巨的
This is not an easy journey. It is difficult
现在维多利亚港上空烟花灿烂
Now Victoria Harbour sky is sparkling...
引来接近四十万的市民 在维多利亚港两旁观赏
attracting almost 400,000 people in both sides of the harbourto see
一起庆祝香港回归祖国
Together celebrating Hong Kong's return to the motherland
誉玲，你记得吗？我曾经对你提过…
Remember, Yue-ling? I mentioned to you before...
在我的牢房窗口看出去的那一座山
about the hill that I see from the window of my cell
每次当我看著那山的时候
Every time when I look at it,
当我知道自己无法见到山后面 是怎样的时候
when I can't see what's behind it
我就很害怕，觉得很恐怖
I feel frightened, and am horrified
前面我什么都看不见
I can see nothing ahead of me
以后的日子，我真不知道怎么过
I don't know how to spend the rest of my life
把我们提出来后弄来一个“酌情终身”
After discussing our case, they gave us back discretionary life sentence
我们等候英女皇发落变成等候特首发落
Detained at HM's pleasure changed to detained at the CE's pleasure
那粱忠勤可靠得吗？
Is that Leung Chung-ken reliable?
你别这样说粱先生，他已经尽了力的了
Don't say that, he has already tried his best
我们搞一个监狱绝食抗议行动
We're going to have a hunger strike
你去告诉记者！
You go and notify the press!
你不要胡来，这样会影响法官 判你的刑期的
Don't lose control, it might affect the judge's sentence
粱先生说虽然他已不是议员， 他还是会尽力帮我们
Mr. Leung said, although he's no longer a Councillor
他们不再会特别为我安排探监了
They won't have special arrangment for me to see you.
以后我会减少来看你的时间
I won't come so frequently...
我不想妨碍你家人的探期
because I don't want to shorten yourfamily's visits
其实我妈年纪大了
In fact, my mom is old
我也不希望她老远地跑来看我
I don't want herto exhaust herself coming here
她始终是你妈
She's your mom, after all
首席大法官会根据你的案子 和你多年的表现…
The Chief Justice will suggest a sentence...
给你一个建议服刑期
based on your case and your performance in jail overthe past years
特首就会根据这个建议服刑期.
The Chief Executive will give you a determinate sentence...
给你一个确定刑期
based on the suggested sentence
你不用担心，我会写求情信给特首的了
Don't worry! I'll send a letter of appeal to the Chief Executive
谢谢！
Thank you!
粱先生，你们先走好了！
We'll say goodbye here, Mr. Leung!
我想在附近走一走
I want to take a walk here
好的！
OK!
小铭，我记得你向我提过
Ming: I recalled the hill that you mentioned before
在你牢房窗口看出去的那一座山
the hill you can see from the window of your cell
今天我上山去替你看过了
I went up there to look on your behalf today
山后面是一个水塘，那儿的风景很美
What's behind it is a reservoir with a very nice landscape
我希望有一天你能到这儿来
I hope one day you can come...
看看水塘美丽的景色
to see the beautiful scenery of the reservoiryourself
司机，麻烦你，我要下车
Let me get off, please!
找死也不要害我啊
Don't give me trouble even if you want to kill yourself
有没有看今天的报纸？
Have you read today's newspaper?
这里，你看看这篇文章！
Here! Read this article
粱先生呢？
Where's Mr. Leung?
在里面
In there!
粱先生…  什么事？
Mr. Leung... Yes?
快，来看看这一则新闻
Come! Come and read this news
当年宝马山双尸案受害者的家属
The families of the Braemar Hill couple were in deep grief
事隔十二年，他们已经 从仇恨中恢复过来
After 12 years, their hatred has healed
还懂得宽恕别人， 写信给特首为当年的凶手求情
and they can forgive; so they sent the CE a letter begging for mercy
这信对我们很有帮助
This letter will help us a lot
对啊！
Yes!
这下我们有希望了
We have hope now this time!
好消息…好消息，快来！
Good news... good news, come on!
关掉水龙头！来…
Turn the tap off! Come...
你们看…
Look...
宝马山双尸案的事，那死者的父亲
The Braemar Hill couple's father...
写信给政府，原谅小铭当年年少无知
wrote the government a letter, and forgave Ming's ignorance
还求情说给他减刑
He also begged for mercy and for reducing his sentence
太好了…
This is just great...
别开心得太早，能马上出去吗？
Don't get excited too soon! You can't get out of here right now, can you?
起码会比你早！
I'll be out of here earlierthan you, at least!
妈，我是你女儿誉玲
Mom: This is your daughter, Yue-ling
今天我在报纸看到宝马山双尸案死者 家属的消息
I read about the Braemar Hill couple's families in the newspapertoday
他们写信给特首为当年 杀害自己子女的凶手求情
They wrote the CE a letter asking for clemency forthe murderers
想不到事隔十二年， 他们也学会了去宽恕一个罪人
I didn't expect them to learn to forgive after 12 years
而我竟然生了你十二年的气
While I have been mad at you forthe last 12 years
我有一个好朋友， 很小便没有见过他的亲母
I have a good friend who hasn't seen his mom since he was very small
他很想找回他妈妈
He wants to see his mom so much
这是他一生中最大的愿望
That is the biggest hope in his life
而我…
And I...
有一个可以随时见到的妈妈
have a mother I can see any time,
但是为何这许多年来 都没回家见你一面？
yet all these years I didn't want to come home to see you
妈！
Mom!
妈，这条裙子都烂成这样了， 你还没扔？
This dress is so torn, and you haven't thrown it away, Mom?
你那么喜欢那条裙子
You liked that dress so much
我怎么舍得扔掉呢？
How can I throw it away?
妈，你不想知道这十二年我 都去了哪儿了？
Don't you want to know where I have been forthe past 12 years, Mom?
你要想说的话，你早就说了
You'd have told me long ago if you wanted to
你要是不想说
There's no point in asking you...
我问你也没用！
if you didn't
刚开始我在一家电子厂当工人
I first worked at an electronics factory
后来我认识了一个比我 大二十几岁的男人
Then I met a man who was about 20 years olderthan me
他供我读书，就像当年表姨丈那样
He paid for my school, just like my uncle
我知道表姨丈的事
I realise what happened between me and uncle...
我也不知道啊！
I didn't understand then!
小时候我很恨香港， 我不知道你为什么要带我来
I hated Hong Kong very much when you wanted to take me here
我也不想伤你的心
I don't want to hurt you
但是过去的事
But no one can change...
谁也改变不了
what happened in the past
妈，我现在挺好的
Mom, I'm fine now
我现在觉得…
And now I feel...
我们应该在一起住
we should live together
我还想…喝你煮给我的汤
I also very much want to drink the soup you make!
好！
Fine!
汤都凉了，赶快喝，来！
The soup is getting cold. Come on, drink quick!
多喝点…
Drink some more...
很好喝！
Very delicious!
好喝！
Delicious!
多喝！
Drink more!
1998年7月
July of 1998
坐下！
Sit!
今天叫你们到这儿来…
We sent foryou today...
是因为你们的刑期报告已经来了
because your sentence reports have arrived
一会儿狱长会亲自向你们宣布
The warden will announce them to you himself in a moment
进来！
Come in!
长官早！ 犯人到齐了
Good morning, Sir! The offenders are all here!
叫他们一个一个进来！
Send them in one by one!
59827，进去！
59827, go in!
别紧张，现在可不是判你们死刑！
Don't be nervous! You are not sentenced to death!
60132，进去！
60132, go in!
不可能！那些家伙在耍我
Lmpossible! Those guys are ripping me off!
他们耍了我十几年了！
They've been ripping me off for 10 years or so!
冷静点儿…
Calm down...
别闹…坐下…
Don't mess up! Sit!
我要出去！
I want to get out of here!
你们耍了我十几年了！
You've been ripping me off for 10 years or so!
你们耍了我十几年还没耍够吗？
Isn't it enough?
董建华（香港特别行政区首长） ， 你这老糊涂！
Tung Chee Wah (Chief Executive of the SAR), you are senile!
耍了我十几年了！
Been ripping me off forten years!
放我出去…
Let me out...
怎么搞的？
I can't believe this!
下一个！
Next!
67544，进去！
Go in, 67544!
早，Sir！
Good morning, Sir!
坐吧！
Sit!
67544，终审庭首席大法官 看了你的个案
67544, Andrew Li of the Court of Final Appeal has looked into your case
他建议你的最低必须服刑期是三十年
He recommended a minimum term of 30 years
特区首长董建华同意他的建议
The CE, Tung Chee Wah, already agreed to his recommendation
在这三十年里，你没有假期、没福利
You will have no benefits or holidays in these 30 years
也不能申请假释
Neither can you apply for parole
在这段期间
During this period of time,
长囚会每两年会复检你的案子
The LTDRC will review your case every 2 years
然后再考虑你的实际刑期
and will consideryour actual term
我想上诉
I want to appeal
这是行政决定，你不能上诉
You can't appeal since this is an executive decision
如果你坚持，你可以试一试
You may try if you insist
你出去吧！
You may go!
市民听说二十年、 三十年还以为很合理
People find 20 years or 30 years very reasonable
但他们不知道这些刑期 跟其他犯人不同
What they don't know is these terms are different from other offenders
无缘无故在刑期前面 加“最低”两个字
The word minimum was added for no reason
最低服刑期还不等于无限期再等？
Isn't minimum term the same as endless waiting?
粱先生，电话
Mr. Leung, phone!
我是…
Speaking...
谢谢你！
Thank you!
惩教署的辅导员打电话来
Correctional Services Department called...
说那些孩子的情绪不好
and said those kids became emotional
所以监狱这个月破例， 让家属无限次探监
So the prison is breaking the rules to allow unrestricted family visits
小发，你的主意最多
You have strong opinions, Fatt!
现在我们这样子，怎么办？
In a situation like this, what can we do?
找个人寻死，告诉政府我们的不满
Pick someone to commit suicide, to tell the government we are unsatisfied
让我来吧！
I'll do it!
不要！
No!
你是监狱社工，监友需要你
You're a prison social worker, the inmates need you
让我来！
Let me go!
不要！想你妈哭死不成？
No! You want to break your mom's heart?
我以前是帮老大才进来的
I ended up here because I helped our Chief...
我现在希望为弟兄们做点事
Now I really want to do something foryou guys
那也轮不到你呀！
You cannot do this!
这里全靠你了
You're the only one left
别争了，我刑期最长
Don't fight, my term is the longest
这个抗议，让我来吧！
Let me take up the demonstration!
致宝马山死者的家属
To the families of the Braemar Hill dead:
我是宝马山双尸案犯人之一，张有铭
This is one of the Braemar Hill offenders, Cheung Yau-ming
我知道一句对不起无法补偿什么
I understand one Sorry can't remedy anything
但我还是想对你们说一句：对不起
But I still want to say, Sorry!
当年我以为是跟著老大去抢劫
At the time, I thought I was just stealing with our Chief
没想到会搞出了人命
I didn't expect it would take human lives
当时老大给了我一根棍子
The Chief gave me a rod
他说随便打两下
He said I should strike with it a couple of times...
表示人人有份
to show that everybody's involved
要不然就打死我
Otherwise he'd kill me
我知道犯了罪就该被惩罚
I understand one should be penalised if he commits a crime
但是我觉得这个最低必须服刑期 已经不是惩罚
but I find this minimum term of 30 years is already not a penalty,
而是一种摧毁
it's a ruin
但是无论如何
However,
我还是要感谢你们在承受 失去儿女的痛苦之后
I still thank foryourforgiveness...
还能宽恕我、原谅我
after suffering the loss of children
现在我用我的性命
Now I give my life...
亲自向你们谢罪！
to apologise to you!
小铭…为什么这样？小铭
Ming... Why are you doing that? Ming!
小铭…别这样，小铭！
Ming... Don't! Ming!
不要啊！小铭…
Don't, Ming!
不要…不要…
Don't... don't...
小铭，你不要死！别这样！
Ming, don't die! Don't do that!
快放我出去！
Let me out!
有人吗？救命啊！
Is anybody out there? Help!
小铭！
Ming!
天啊！小铭呀！
God! Ming!
小铭…阿Sir，来呀，来人啊！阿Sir
Ming... Sir, please! Sir! Sir!
救命啊…
Help!
阿Sir，小铭出事了，快点…
Sir! Something's wrong with Ming, quick!
阿发，小铭怎么样？
How's Ming, Fatt?
小铭怎么样？他怎么样了？
How's Ming?
张有铭，你在干什么？
What are you doing, Cheung Yau-ming?
没事！
Nothing!
小铭…
Ming...
小铭，你没事了？
Ming, are you all right?
我没事！
I'm OK!
小铭，你没事了？
Are you OK, Ming?
你吓死我了！
You scared the shit out of me!
我没事！
I'm OK!
你没事？没事？
Are you OK? OK?
我们没事！
We're OK!
你怎么样？
How do you feel?
对不起！
Sorry!
你吓死我了，知道吗？
You know you scared me to death?
没事！没事就好了！
That's good!
别这样，小子！
Don't be like that, damn you!
你没错！不关你的事
It's not yourfault!
你吓死我了！
You scared me to death!
怎么了？
What's wrong?
我花了那么多精力和时间
I spent so much time and energy
还是帮不了他们
and still can't help them
但是起码可以让他们知道，世界上…
Well, at least they know...
还有你这样的人关心他们，对吧？
there are still people like you who care forthem, right?
誉玲，时间是公平的
Yue-ling, time is just
不论开心或不开心
Whether happy or unhappy,
始终都要过去
it will pass after all
三十年，一万零九百五十天
30 years, 10,950 days
我每天都会数著日子
I'll count every day
昨天我差点儿自杀了
I nearly killed myself yesterday
但是我没有死
But I didn't!
因为我相信
Because I believe that...
终有一天我会见到我的亲生母亲
I'll meet my natural mother one day
我会好好念书
I'll study hard
我答应你，我会考得最好
I promise you, I'll get highest grades
希望在颁奖礼的时候
I hope to see you...
可以见到你
at the awards ceremony
和你握手
We'll shake hands then
我答应你！
I promise you!
你找谁？
Who are you looking for?
你好！我替朋友找他妈妈
Hi! I'm helping my friend to look for his mother
找妈妈？！
Looking for a mother?
我朋友叫张有铭，他妈妈叫潘有莲
My friend is called Cheung Yau-ming; his mother is called Poon Yau-lin
我不认识这个人
I don't know this person
他们以前就住在这儿
They used to live here
我这里有一张照片，你看看…
I have a picture here, look...